Devansh Popat

■ +1(773)739-3951 ■ dpopat3@uic.edu ■ <u>LinkedIn</u> ■ <u>GitHub</u>

SUMMARY

Aspiring Data Scientist with 2+ years of progressive experience in data reporting and analytics. Proficient in producing advanced predictive models and reporting profitability using Python and MS Excel. Disciplined and Organized team player with the ability to communicate and present effectively.

EDUCATION

Master of Science, Major: Management Information Systems **University of Illinois at Chicago,** Chicago, IL

Jun 2018 – Dec 2019 GPA: 3.41/4

Bachelor of Engineering, Electronics and Telecommunications Engineering **University of Mumbai**, Mumbai, India

Jul 2013 – May 2017 GPA: 3.3/4

SKILLS

- Languages: SQL (Advanced), Python (Advanced), R (Advanced), SAS, Java.
- Tools: Power BI, Tableau, SSRS, SSAS, MicroStrategy, MS Office (Excel, Word, PowerPoint, Outlook, Access).
- Libraries: Python Pandas, Matplotlib, Scikit-learn, fastai, PySpark; R dplyr, tidyverse, ggplot2, car, plotly.
- Certifications: Python for Data Science, Tableau 10, Oracle DB Associate: 11g, MS SQL Server 2016.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

UI Health Chicago, IL
Database Assistant Aug 2018 – Present

- Analyzed & tracked 500+ outpatient registrations per day with MS-Excel & Cerner Millennium based tool.
- Improved patient discharge volume and wait time by 20% using plots in Ambulatory Operations dashboard.
- Abetted the team to extract, transform and load the data into the SQL Server using nested SQL queries.

Technology: MicroStrategy, MS SQL Server, MS Office (Excel, Outlook, Word).

ANJ Web Tech Junior Data Analyst Strategy and Analytics Intern Ahmedabad, India Jun 2017 – May 2018 Jan 2017 – Mar 2017

- Created and Monitored weekly sales dashboards to deliver insights and trends to product sales metrics.
- Optimized the cart-removal rate by 15% by designing and building statistical models on large datasets.
- Estimated customer purchase behavior by cleaning, visualizing the data and boosted the ROI by 10,000\$.

Technology: MS SQL Server (SSRS, SSAS), Power BI, MS Office (Excel, PowerPoint).

Achievements: Employee of the month accolade (March 2018), ISTQB Certification (Foundation Level).

PROJECTS

Walmart Store Sales Forecasting (Python, MS Excel)

- Analyzed the effect of trend, seasonality and implemented statistical methods to forecast the weekly sales.
- Suggested top performing departments using interactive graphs to up sales by up to 50,000 USD/year.

Breast Cancer Detection (R, MS Excel)

- Identified major cancer-causing cells by cleaning, wrangling, and visualizing 2 million data points.
- Helped laboratory to improvise the patient treatment by a 92% accurate data-driven decision tree model.

American Airlines on-time Performance (2018) (Tableau)

- Developed stories using visual depictions of key flight delay metrics to identify closest airline competitors.
- Recommended solutions to reduce delay in flights for different cities by utilizing motion charts.

PUBG Finish Placement Prediction (Python)

- Predicted the final ranking for each of the 5 million players using cross-validated random forest model.
- Aided in increasing the gaming users by providing best winning strategy using feature importance plots.

Customer Churn Prediction (Python)

- Suggested customized plans for customer groups based on demographic information using kNN.
- Provided recommendations to avoid customer churn in future with interactive line and bar graphs.